"Book Trailer for How Not to Age"
There may be no such thing
as dying from old age.
From a study of more than 42,000
consecutive autopsies,
centenarians—those who live
past one hundred—
were found to have succumbed
to diseases
in 100 percent
of the cases examined.
Though most were perceived,
even by their physicians,
to have been healthy
just prior to death,
not one “died of old age.”
They died from disease,
most commonly heart attack.
If aging kills via diseases,
why wasn’t my book
How Not to Die all the longevity
book anyone needs?
In it, I ran through
what we can do to prevent, arrest,
or reverse each of our 15
leading causes of death,
starting with heart disease, not only
the #1 killer of centenarians,
but of men and women in general,
and projected to remain that way
in the decades to come.
But is it really?
Because the single greatest
risk factor
for most of our killer diseases
is old age,
one could argue that
the leading cause of death
is actually aging.
The rate of death
increases exponentially
for age-related diseases
such as heart disease, cancer,
stroke, dementia.
So yes, in the same age bracket,
having a high cholesterol
can increase
your risk of heart disease
as much as twentyfold,
but an 80-year-old
may have 500 times the risk
of having a heart attack compared
to someone in their twenties.
Yes, eating a plant-based diet
may reduce the risk of dementia
as much as threefold,
but the difference
in dementia rates
between those older than 85
compared to younger
than 65 is 300-fold.
The reason we focus
on things like cholesterol
is because it’s a modifiable
risk factor.
But what if the rate of aging
was modifiable too?
Instead of our current
piecemeal approach
of focusing on individual
degenerative diseases,
what about slowing down
the aging process itself?
I can remember as a nerdy kid
I wanted to cure cancer
when I grew up.
But even if all forms
of cancer were eliminated,
the average life expectancy
in the US
would only go up
about three years. Why?
Because dodging cancer
would just mean delaying death
from something like
a heart attack or stroke.
If one age-related ailment
doesn’t get us, another will.
Rather than playing
“whack-a-mole”
by tackling each
disease separately,
progress in decelerating
aging could address
all these issues simultaneously.
Imagine if there
was an intervention
that didn’t just reduce your risk
of the leading killers,
but also arthritis, osteoporosis,
sensory impairments.
Even just slowing aging seven years,
such that the average
65-year-old, for example,
would have the health profile
and disease risk
of today’s 58-year-old,
would be expected to cut
everyone’s risk of death, frailty,
and disability in half
(because such risks tend
to double every seven years).
That’s why I wrote How Not to Age.
The problem is
the anti-aging field
is said to be a “fertile ground
for cons, scams,
and get-rich-quick schemes.”
As a former president of the
Gerontological Society of America
has written, there have been
“few subjects which have been
more misleading
to the uncritical
and more proﬁtable
to the unscrupulous.”
Not only does the popular
literature on the subject harbor
a “huge amount of misinformation,”
but most anti-aging scientists
widely known to the public
are said to be “unscrupulous
purveyors of useless nostrums,”
according to the editor-in-chief
of a leading gerontology journal.
It's easy to be swayed
by charismatic gurus,
but when it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as the health and well-being
of ourselves and our families,
we should rely not on anecdote,
but on evidence.
That’s why I cite everything
to the teeth.
How Not to Die had about
2,000 citations;
How Not to Diet, 5,000;
How Not to Age ended up
with 13,000 citations,
all of which I have hyperlinked
for you online to access
the original sources.
My inspiration for writing
How Not to Age
was a consensus document
entitled "Interventions
to Slow Aging in Humans"
compiled by the top researchers
in anti-aging medicine
(the likes of Drs. Longo, Sinclair,
Fontana, a veritable Who’s Who).
They were brought together to identify
the most promising strategies
to combat aging.
They identified a list of
“essential pathways,”
for example, drugs that can block
the hormone IGF-1,
or drugs to block
the enzyme TOR.
As I looked through
the list, I realized:
Wait, every single one of these pathways
could be regulated through diet.
That became the opening
section of this book.
The science of aging
has been called
“the most dynamic and provocative
in modern biology.”
An attempt to classify
the theories of aging published
more than 30 years ago identified
more than 300 such theories,
and the number
has only grown since.
In Part I, I identify the 11
most promising pathways
for slowing the sands of time,
ending each with practical proposals
for targeting them each
naturally with suggestions
for diet and lifestyle changes.
Part II targets the optimal
anti-aging regimen.
The odds of living
to age 100 have risen
from approximately 1 in 20 million
to as high as 1 in 50.
Why do some make it
and others not?
It’s not just a matter
of picking better parents.
Studies following identical twins
suggest that only
about 25 percent
of the variation in lifespan
is explained by gene inheritance.
The media loves stories
about hard-living centenarians
who attribute their longevity
to some combination
of lard, vodka, and their favorite
brand of cigarette.
But how do centenarians
and supercentenarians
(those over 110)
really eat and live?
What are the best and worst
foods and beverages?
What about red wine, and
fish, olive oil, coffee?
I cover the "longevity vitamin"
ergothioneine,
the vegetarian’s Achilles’ heel,
and the ideal exercise
and sleep routines.
Then in Part III, I get into
the nitty gritty.
What can we do to preserve our bones,
bowels, bladder, and circulation;
your hair, hearing,
and hormone balance;
your immune function
and joint health;
your mind, your muscles;
your sex life and skin;
your teeth, your vision, and finally,
your dignity in death?
There are chapters on each.
Did you know that 85 percent
of bone fracture risk
has nothing to do with
your bone mineral density?
I address that in the
“Preserving Your Bones” chapter,
talking about the pros and cons
of the new osteoporosis drugs,
what supplements to consider,
as well as more natural approaches
to protect your skeleton.
I discuss preserving
your bowel function,
fittingly, in chapter number two.
I discuss solutions
to the constipation epidemic,
proper positioning,
laxatives, fiber supplements.
I also compare the six colon cancer
screening strategies
and ways to help prevent it
in the first place,
as well as bladder function—
urinary incontinence,
and prostate enlargement.
In the circulation chapter, I discuss
how having a "normal" cholesterol
or blood pressure is not
so good in a society
where it’s normal
for people to drop dead
of heart attacks and strokes.
I cover statins and stents
and, most importantly,
treating the underlying cause
of artery function failure.
“Preserving Your Hair” refers
to both color and volume.
Why do we gray and lose our hair,
and what we can do about it?
I also cover drugs,
supplements, and surgeries,
as well as dietary
and topical treatments.
In “Preserving Your Hearing”
I break down hearing aids,
earwax removal,
and the fact that, in some cultures,
there’s no such thing
as age-related hearing loss.
What can we learn from them
to protect our own inner ears?
In the hormone chapter,
I investigate blockbuster
anti-aging “treatments”
like growth hormone injections,
DHEA, the preservation
of female fertility,
menopausal hormone therapy,
natural alternatives for symptoms
like hot flashes, and the pros
and cons of testosterone therapy
for so-called male “andropause.”
In the immunity chapter,
I cover immune-boosting foods
to improve cancer surveillance
and resistance to infection,
examine the role of supplements
like ginseng, vitamin D, and zinc,
and help you decide
whether to get vaccinated
against the flu,
pneumonia, and shingles.
The joint chapter
touches on back pain,
but focuses on osteoarthritis,
covering prescription and
over-the-counter drugs, injections,
knee surgery, topical treatments,
inflammation-dousing foods,
and supplements, such as
glucosamine and chondroitin.
“Preserving Your Mind”
takes on the dementia epidemic.
I cover Alzheimer’s disease,
vascular dementia,
the rapidly reversible
causes of dementia,
the controversial new drugs,
so-called "brain supplements"
like ginkgo,
the role of aluminum
and chronic infections like HSV,
and, most importantly,
what we can do to prevent, arrest,
and even rewind
cognitive decline.
In “Preserving Your Muscles,”
I tackle what we can do
to combat age-related
muscle loss and frailty,
addressing protein
needs of older adults
and supplements like creatine,
as well as touch on
essential tremor.
Then, it’s on to
“Preserving Your Sex Life.”
I discuss the best ways,
natural and otherwise,
to improve male and female
sexual interest and function.
I talk about aging body odor,
the best vaginal moisturizers
and lubricants,
and the role of herbs,
such as ashwagandha
and maca root.
(I’ll understand if you want
to skip directly to this chapter.)
Then, it’s all about skincare.
I cover the pros and cons
of chemical peels,
laser resurfacing,face-lifts,
Botox, and filler injections;
how we can prevent
and treat wrinkles both topically
and from the inside
out by what we eat.
What’s the safest sunscreen?
What’s the value
of facial moisturizers,
alpha hydroxy acids, retinoids,
collagen supplements,
and anti-aging skin creams
and serums?
I also cover varicose veins
and nail health,
from brittle fingernails
to fungal toenails,
and the role of nail supplements
like biotin.
In “Preserving Your Teeth,”
I take a bite out
of periodontal disease
and tooth loss,
cover oil pulling and fluoride,
and detail the best mouthwash.
In the vision chapter, I focus
on dietary approaches to cataracts,
glaucoma, and macular degeneration,
including the role
of lutein and zeaxanthin.
And the final chapter in the section,
“Preserving Your Dignity,”
offers the assurance
that you can have control
over your ultimate fate.
The final section,
“Dr. Greger's Anti-Aging Eight,”
is intended to be an actionable
checklist to complement
my Daily Dozen
from How Not to Die.
In addition to the wealth
of recommendations
throughout the book,
this section is designed
to highlight specific foods,
supplements,
or behaviors that have
the potential to offer
the best opportunities to slow
aging or improve longevity.
My aim with this book was to cover
every possible angle
for developing the optimal diet
and lifestyle for the longest,
healthiest lifespan based on the best
available balance of evidence.